Hi, there was some people who wanted me
to take a closer look at the Energy
Micro Tiny Gecko board. Power it up,
hook it up, do some measurements. Sounds
like a good idea. Let's go.
Now, there were a few people who
commented on the mark on the LCD here.
It's not a mark at all. It's just the
Tada! The uh plastic film protecting the
display. Now, let's actually power the
thing up and see what happens. Woohoo!
Get latest software from
energymicro.com.
Not too keen on the uh segmented display
here. Oh, it's got a nice little um
fancy uh target display there, custom
display. And it's jump straight into
what looks like the uh cap sense slider
thing. So, let's play around with that.
Whoa, yeah, it does work. Let's touch it
over here.
And you'll notice that that dash
disappears and then it's giving you a
count, which is presumably
the count position on the slider. And if
I slide my
finger along there, not only does that
bar graph
rotational bar graph go up, but uh cap
sense touch also
goes along and scrolls the text. Cap
sense demo. It's a little bit touchy,
pardon the pun, but uh you can see that
works a treat. And if you push the
button here, you end up in a slider
thing which actually
Well, it slides the segments along the
display like that instead of scrolling
the text. And uh if you do it again,
it's got uh looks like a pad zero, I
assume refers to that pad. And you can
see the value change. And if I touch
these pads over here, it doesn't really
change at all. And I can swap between
pad one. If I touch pad one there, the
value changes. If I touch pad zero,
doesn't really change that much. So,
there you go. It looks like it comes up
pre-loaded with uh uh only a cap sense
demo. Could have something else, but I
can't find it. There's one thing I
didn't see in the original look at this
was this LC sensor here. It's a little
inductor and it can detect nearby
magnetic fields. And but don't get too
excited. You're not going to be able to
take this thing out and find Lassiter's
reef or anything like that. It's only
got a detection range of a couple of
millimeters, I believe. And I did
complain that there wasn't a gecko on
the board and sure enough previous
versions of the board have had a gecko,
but the one I've got they've taken it
off. But on the chip there, you can see
cute little gecko laser etched onto the
chip. I love it. And this switch down
here turns it off and on from the
battery power, but let's hook it up to
the USB and see what we get.
Tada! Ping! And it powers it
alternatively from the USB and we've got
our uh Seger J-Link debugger LEDs going
there. So, let's give the software a
try. And the only documentation you get
in the box is this quick start guide
which says go to
energymicro.com/simplicity.
Well, let's give it a try. And bingo!
You type in energymicro.com/simplicity
and you get this page a step-by-step
procedure to run the software. Looks
pretty easy. Let's give it a try. And
here it is Simplicity Studio free
download and it it appears that they've
got different demo boards. This is the
tiny gecko, but they have other ones
with large
RGB type displays on them. And looks
like the software would support all of
those. So, let's download it and there's
a whole bunch of demo programs.
Beautiful. Let's give it a try.
And I won't bore you with the entire
download process. It was a 7 meg
download, very reasonable size and it
popped up with this, "The following
recommended packages are not installed.
Do you wish to install them?"
Ah.
Eh, better. On second thought, screw
that. It's taking too long, so I'm going
to cancel that, and I'll see what
happens when I plug in the board. And it
looks like you have to install
everything, so don't just do what I did
and cancel it. Make sure you install all
the options. And here we go, we get the
energy aware stuff because this Tiny
Gecko board actually has any energy
measurement built in. It's effectively
got like a little microcurrent built
into it. It can
It has two different ranges that can
actually
record the CPU measure and transmit back
and graph the CPU current
for various ranges and power cycle. So,
we'll give that a try, and we've got app
notes, we've got examples, kit
documentation, demos, videos, all sorts
of things. Looks pretty good.
Here's all the uh
documentation. So, let's take a look at
And there's not much on the data sheet,
but it does tell you here it has 0.1
microamps or 100 nanoamps to 50 amps
measurement range of the measures the
voltage and the current of the VMCU
rail, so that measuring voltage and
current allows you to calculate how much
power because the thing with measuring
and characterizing and comparing the
power consumption of different
microcontrollers is just that you have
to do power. You can't necessarily go on
just the current figures because it's
dependent upon the supply voltage. Let's
take a look at the user manual here.
It's 41 pages, seems fairly
comprehensive. And if we take a look at
the block diagram, there's the segmented
display. Look at the tiny little gecko.
They've got a gecko symbol on the
display. Haven't figured out how to get
that one up yet, but that's nice. It's
got a little battery bar graph end uh
the various circular things plus the
segmented display as well and like a
timer display up here too and there's
milliamps, microamps. So maybe if we run
some of the power demo apps it'll
actually tell us how much power is being
consumed. That'd be really nice and
there's the rest of the block diagram
the touch slider, a couple of push
buttons, the ambient light sensor, the
LC sensor as I mentioned uh and some
debug stuff and the optional op-amp and
that's about it. But what I'm really
interested with this thing is the power
management capabilities. And if we click
on the demos button here, what do we
get? We get a whole bunch of demos and
there's a here we go a demo of different
energy modes. Let's have a look at that.
So here it is they got the instructions
here. It basically you just cut and
paste this example code here a tiny
amount. You just put it in your main uh
thing call up this function once by the
looks of it at the start and it looks
like it gives you the the energy profile
of the different functions. Look at that
main is taking 98% of the power I'm
assuming. Yep, energy in microjoules.
There it is and that's brilliant. And
presumably if you got a big complex app,
you can see which functions are taking
the most amount of power. I'm really
liking this because doing this sort of
stuff with a regular microcontroller
which doesn't have the building support
for doing something like this would is
usually very difficult and ad hoc.
You've got to know how much instruction
time is spent in each
subroutine and function and then try and
measure your battery consumption. But
here you can actually do it directly on
the demo board. It looks pretty trivial.
Wow, this is powerful. And what I did is
I clicked on the main function and this
looks like the demo program it's running
e-mode.c
and
you can see the code in here and it's
drawing down the bottom here 5.92
milliamps at 3.3 volts but I don't uh
off hand here I don't know what
frequency that's running at or what it's
actually doing at the moment but you can
actually looks like you can go in and
you can debug your code directly in this
energy aware profiler window. And if you
go into the energy aware battery thing
here it gives you
a tool which allows you to estimate the
battery life of your program. I'm
running a demo
here and it's a see you can choose your
cell alkaline double A triple A or your
CR2032s
for example lithium cells number in
parallel number in series and uh it can
apparently give you a profile boom of
there's the battery curve like that and
it can show you the minimum where you
set your minimum operating
voltage at presumably you can change
that figure average current might be 2.8
microamps here estimated system
operating time 8 years there you go the
rated capacity is on that's a CR2032
cell 8 years at 2.8 microamps that's
rather neat you'd have to like you can
actually load in presumably load in your
actual program and it will
actually estimate it based on your real
application. I'm just running one of the
simulation demos here but this looks
really neat. They've really put a lot of
effort into
energy management on these Gecko
microcontrollers it seems to
what they're actually um them apart so
I like this. Man, this is neat. I think
I might
this is kind of swaying me towards using
an energy micro
device in my MicroWatch Mark II, I
think. Just because the tools are neat.
And if we go into the Energy Aware
Designer program here, this allows you
to generate C code the initialization C
code for various packages and various
peripherals and things like that. So,
you go up here, you choose your device
from all those and all the different
types of packages, and then we can
enable things like enable our real-time
clock.
Bang. You want to do that? We want some
ADCs. Yep, we've got looks like four to
choose from in this particular package.
Let's enable, you know, four channels of
those. And oh, yeah, I squared C. I want
one of those. And looks like you can get
three different
pin locations for the Yeah, there we go.
You can select which pins you want. Oh,
neat.
I like that. And oh, actually it tells
you it conflicts. I'm assuming the red
means that they've conflicted with
something else.
Mhm.
Ah, excellent. All right. I like that.
Otherwise, it's put them up here. And we
enable that and
you can do that with any of the internal
peripherals. We've got the timer, the
interrupts, and stuff like that. And you
can generate PDF reports for this sort
of thing. We can do the We can show pin
matrix views.
There we go. That's a matrix kind of
view. Once again, we can save the
PDF
for that. It's got a button down here,
but let's get out of that and let's
generate our C code.
Bingo. There it is. We've got our C code
for initializing this particular device.
Looks like it's set up as 14 MHz high
frequency clock, GPIO, there's a
um, the PIOs open drain with pull up and
filter and all that's and there's the
ADC, the I squared C. All your
initialized code is there for you. I've
got to say that is one of the better uh,
configuration
tools I've seen from uh, any vendor.
That's very nice cuz a lot a lot of the
pain involved with uh, microcontrollers
is just getting the damn things up and
running and uh, getting the modules
enabled cuz you first write your program
and then, you know, it doesn't work
first go and you're scratching your head
wondering why cuz you haven't enabled
some pin or uh, some register or
something like that. This just allows
you to do it in a nice graphical user
interface and make sure you've got it
right.
Neat.
And let's try out the energy aware
commander option which apparently allows
you to download uh, firmware and do
stuff like that. So, let's connect. It's
we're connected to our tiny gecko uh,
starter kit. Uh, we're in we can go to
uh, various uh, debug
modes, USB address, the chip type we've
got on the board there, the chip
revision. So, it's read the uh, silicon
ID code out of that. We can flash in uh,
there we go. We can flash in uh, various
stuff. So, that's like a little uh,
programmer. Is it? That's almost like a
stand alone programmer
option, I think. So, let's go look in
the demos. There we go. We can download
the demos. Blink the LED. Woohoo! Try
different energy energy mode demo using
the LCD. Let's try that. Start.
And it resets and that's pretty quick
and yep, we've got something on our LCD.
When you press the reset button here,
you can see that it's uh,
in 32 MHz mode and you can actually
cycle through different modes, 32 kHz
crystal, and when you do that, that will
plus the RTC,
the real-time clock. So, you've got all
these different modes that you can
measure, and in the background, you'll
be able to see the graph changing. So,
let's give that a try. So, let's take a
look at that. You can see it's drawing
5.92 milliamps now because it's in the
32 MHz mode. So, that's what it's
drawing at 32 MHz.
5. Almost 6 milliamps at 3.3 volts, but
if we change that mode,
we can see it. Let's go to 32 kHz and
see what happens there. And bang, it's
dropped. And you can see all the
different functions down here where it's
taking the power consumption for this
application. All right, this is really
cool. Check this out. I'll switch it to
32 kHz mode. There it is. And you should
find the current consumption
bang, drops all the way down to 1
microamp because we've got that
logarithmic scale there.
And if I choose the RTC plus LCD option
here, there it is, it'll leave the LCD
on,
and there we go. It takes about
oh, I don't know, 6 7 microamps or
something like that to drive that
segmented LCD plus the plus to have the
32 kHz real-time crystal
uh working at the same time. The touch
slider doesn't seem to be active there
at all, but uh
there you go. That's how much energy's
required. Oh, you can see if I press the
button,
da da da, there we go.
You can see just the slight increase in
energy consumption, and you need to to
that into account in your designs. If
you've got a low value pull-up resistor
on your switch and the user's pressing
that, it's taking a little gulp of
current every time you actually do that.
So, um you really have to optimize the
value of your pull-up resistors on those
user switches.
And if we go and take a look at the
application notes here, they're fairly
comprehensive. Like there's uh fat on an
SD card, Ethernet, all the good stuff,
AES cipher modes, and uh
all sorts of things. There's low energy
UARTs. I like it, but let's go in and
actually see. And here's a list of the
five different energy modes we saw in
the example uh demo that we were just
running. So, mode zero is where the CPU
is running flat chat and it's just uh
you know, everything's chewing as much
power as possible. And then there's
sleep mode, energy mode one, where
basically the CPU is disabled, but uh
and any of the any of the peripherals
using the Here we go. Wait for the
peripheral reflex system, PRS, woohoo,
and the DMA. Um it can actually do
autonomous operations without powering
up the CPU. For example, the timer may
repeatedly trigger an ADC conversion at
a given instance. When the conversion is
complete, the results move to DMA to
RAM. And when a given number of
conversions have been performed, the DMA
then wakes up the CPU using an
interrupt. So, you can basically uh data
log, by the sounds of it, data log uh
things from the ADC without using and
powering up the CPU at all. Brilliant.
Um and then there's deep sleep. And
energy mode two means that there's no
high frequency clocks running at all,
only like uh the low power 32 kHz clock
for doing I squared C stuff, LCD uh
operations, UART operations, analog
comparators, real-time clocks, and some
basic GPIO uh checking. And mode three
is the stop mode, and uh that uh differs
from sleep mode in that uh no
oscillator, apart from the watchdog, is
actually running at all, even the
low-frequency uh one. So, in even in
this mode, you can still do an I²C uh
address check, watchdog of course, um
you can do uh pin interrupts, analog
comparators, and GPIO interrupts without
uh any internal clock running. And
energy mode number four is complete
shutoff mode, where it can draw, so they
claim as little as 20 nanoamps. And the
only way to uh exit that mode and get
back to operation is to uh reset the is
to trigger the reset line or uh cycle
the power. But, this claim of 20
nanoamps, I think we might be able to
check that. Hmm.
Now, as a bit of a uh industry
comparison here, I've got it uh running
in the LCD plus um RTC mode. So, um
trust me, the LCD is actually uh
displaying something here, and it's
running the real-time clock as well. And
as you can see, it's drawing around
about 5 microamps or something like
that, cuz remember this is a logarithmic
um uh
Y axis here. But, if we compare that 5
microamps running with, say, a uh
Microchip uh PIC32MX
um series micro, so I'm comparing an 1
32-bit micro to another, not quite um
apples-to-apples, but, you know,
reasonably close. In the uh low-power RC
mode at 32 kHz, it's going to be drawing
roughly um 100 microamps typical at 3.3
V. So, this thing's uh driving an LCD as
well as running the uh real-time clock,
but I guess the process is not
continuously running at 32 kHz here, but
you get the idea of uh of what you can
actually uh do with just, you know, 10
microamps or something like that.
There's hardly anything uh being used
there at all. Sniff of an oily rag. And
of course, if you put the uh demo in
energy mode uh two, which uh claims on
the LCD that it's uh 32 kHz, so I
presume uh the processor's running at 32
kHz. It may not be running continuously,
but as you can see, it draws um under 1
microamp. Amazing. And if we use uh
energy mode two with the real-time clock
turned on, you can see it's now just a
smidgen on or smidgen over 1 microamp.
And again, if we choose the PIC32 uh MX
series micro as an industry comparison
for an equivalent uh 32-bit micro with
the um real-time clock plus the uh timer
one with the 32 kHz crystal, there we
go. 23 microamps typical, 50 microamps
max. So, the energy micro um using its
uh um ARM Cortex uh M3 plus all its uh
energy management uh capability,
low-power stuff, it draws a 1/23 of
that, only 1 microamp. And I've put the
board into energy mode four, which is
complete shutdown mode. And as you can
see, we're down in the noise, under 100
nanoamps there. It's not really accurate
down here. It might be say 10 nanoamps
average, but really it's not accurate at
all. So, let's see if we can get some
more accurate measurements of that. And
if you read the user manual here, it
actually tells you what it's capable of
measuring. Here it is, from 0.1
microamps to 50 milliamps. And does that
in uh two different uh ranges. And uh it
can go down to 100 nanoamps resolution,
but resolution's different to accuracy.
But the built-in uh power measurement uh
capability, you know, it's probably good
enough for uh most applications, but I
think we'll just uh double-check that
and uh see if we can measure it
ourselves. And if we take a look at the
the
here and see how it's doing the MCU
power uh current sense. This is the
circuit it's using a linear technologies
LTC6102
zero drift precision current sense IC.
In fact, it's got two of them for one
for range one and one for range two as
well. And it's it's not a bad device at
all and it's a current sense amplifier.
And if we take a look up here, we've got
an LP3982.
That's a low drop out voltage regulator
for the
for the supply for the CPU and 5 volts
in 3.3 volts out. And there's our
current shunt resistor the 4R7 there.
And of course, it taps off those two
values down into the current sense
amplifier down here for both
ranges. And then the output is switched
in here. There's our coin cell battery
and our output there goes to our
VMCU
in there. So that goes to the
to a specific pin which goes on to the
microcontroller which is just for the
MCU core. So we can measure the power
consumption of that. And by looking at
this, this is some sort of connector or
some sort of test pad. If we look at
R704 here zero ohm resistor, we should
be able to get in there and use that. If
we take desolder that resistor, we
should be able to break into that with
my micro current adapter and actually
measure the current taken by the MCU
pin. Let's give it a go.
And if we take a look at our board here,
we can see our 4.7 ohm current shunt
resistor there with the
two resistors going off into the two
current shunt amplifier chips. And
here's our ST700 connector down here.
And that's our 704. So if we desolder
that sucker, we should be able to get in
there and measure the current
consumption really nicely using this
header connector. I love it. And bingo,
we now have a current shunt in there. We
can just take that out and we can
measure our microcontroller power
consumption. They were thinking when
they designed this because it's energy
micron, they want you to be able to
um measure the energy that this micro is
using. Go figure. And what I've got here
now is my micro current on the uh
milliamp range at the moment hooked in.
Jump it into that um
uh current shunt and shunt uh header
uh connector up there and I've got the
output connected to the fluke on
millivolt range. So, 1 uh millivolt
equals 1 milliamp. So, it's drawing 4.8
milliamps at the moment and that's in
its default uh 32 MHz uh mode. So, if we
let that go down, it's 2.8, switches
off, bang, it goes into the mode. So, we
can measure the different modes now by
just cycling through and selecting the
mode we want. Let's go to that 32K
range
mode. Go down there and uh let's measure
the consumption of that. We're only
talking There it is, that 1 microamp.
But, of course, we can get much better
resolution on that this by switching to
our nanoamp range down here and then
taking it up and bingo, there we go, 990
odd milliamps. It's jumping around. We
could smooth that out if we wanted to,
but it's drawing around that 1 microamp
figure. Now, of course, the big question
is what happens in that um
uh power mode four where it's completely
shut down? Well, we'll find out in a
second.
Bingo, it's dropped down to nothing.
Let's switch this down to our
nanoamp range and uh
1 millivolt, it's drawing not
That's a bit disappointing. It's drawing
100 Oh, no, it's going down. There we
go. So, obviously something has charged
up
there and uh it's got to go down. So, I
might wait a bit and see what that gets
down to. And there you go. When we power
it from the USB input like this, it
actually enables the
some of the energy management stuff and
some of the analog switches and things.
So, you really need to power it from the
USB to get that capability. And there we
go. It's about 165 or 160 odd
nanoamps
power consumption. Energy Microchip
around 20 nanoamps in energy mode for
that complete shutdown mode. So, I
decided to have a look at the schematic
again and see what is on that VMCU pin.
And it turns out there it is. There's
another device on there. It's a
TS3A4751.
And that's a Texas Instruments
single supply quad analog switch. And if
you go down here and take a look at its
current consumption, there it is at 25°
C, which is it's near enough to that
here in the lab. It's around about Well,
no, actually, it's saying that's a
maximum figure there. A maximum figure
of 75
nanoamps. So, you know, but that could
vary quite significantly, I'm sure. But
at least a good part of that current is
coming from this device.
So, then what that's doing is powering
this analog switch here, which has the
JTAG signals going through it. So, I'm
not sure why they're powering that
device.
Well, I guess you've got to measure
allows you to measure the MCU power
consumption during JTAG debug
operations, I suppose. But there you go.
There's the VMCU target and the VMCU
debug there are the things that go down
and power the microcontroller. So, it
looks like that's a bit of
I don't know if it's an it's not really
an oversight, I guess, but it's just a
design thing that doesn't allow you to
accurately measure the just the raw core
power consumption of this thing. And
bingo, I hate these moldy sheet
schematics. They're rather confusing,
but and VMCU not only powers
this analog switch here, but there's
another analog switch. Here it is, VMCU
also powers U695B
there. So, there's another device. So,
there's two of those devices there at 75
micro 75 nanoamps
maximum, which brings us to 150, and
we're measuring 160. So, really,
it, you know, it it comes out in the
end. It works. It's the micro is around
about
20 nanoamp 10 or 20 nanoamps or so
according to
the data sheets, but this isn't going to
be very precise because you've got
you're measuring the power consumption
of these devices as well, these analog
switches, which is going to vary with
temperature, and the micro is going to
vary with temperature as well. So,
unfortunately, that
jumper on there does allow us to measure
the current, but there's that residual
in there.
It allows you to measure the current of
your micro under test except for that
very deep sleep mode where you can't
really characterize the 20 nanoamps.
What a bummer, but I'm not sure it will
actually meet its spec. I'm sure they've
done their homework, and they've done
their isolated measurements there, but
that's still
handy for developing your applications
just using that jumper
shunt there, and you can measure the
in-circuit current, or you can do it
using the on-board energy management
thing. So, there you go. I rather like
that. That's a bit of playing around
with the energy micro EFM32
Tiny Gecko starter kit. Now, I really
I think I like these devices. They live
up to their name, energy micro. They're
all about measuring the energy
consumption and different energy modes
of these microcontrollers. So, next time
you're in the market for
one of these for a low power micro,
check them out. That's energy micro. So,
if you like the video, please give it a
thumbs up and you can discuss it all on
the forum. Catch you next time.
And this is rather neat. I've got it in
LCD mode here and I disconnect the
power, break it, and
it fades away a bit because it's still
storing energy in the bypass caps and
that's what's still powering the
circuit. It still keeps it alive
for quite a few seconds and even when
you think it's dead, it can come back.
Beautiful.